Finding Aid for the William Bellin Papers, 1930-1996
UCLA Library, Performing Arts Special Collections
William Bellin Papers
1930-1996
295
Bellin, William
4 Boxes 2 (linear ft); 4 Flat Oversize Boxes; 15 Oversize Map Folders
William Bellin was a costume, prop and set designer in the performing arts industry. In the course of his career, he was involved with a wide variety of projects including working with the UCLA Theatre Arts Department, Margaret Buxton's Originals, Irvin and Kenneth Feld, and production designer George Jenkins. The collection consists mainly of materials related to his professional career as graphic artist and designer and includes blueline set drawings; costume and prop sketches; playbills; graphic design samples; photographs and transparencies of display materials; and snapshots of scenic elements, floats and props.
University of California, Los Angeles. Library. Performing Arts Special Collections. Los Angeles, California 90095-1575
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Open for research. Advance notice required for access. Contact the UCLA Library, Performing Arts Special Collections Reference Desk for paging information.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Miss Norah Jones.
Biography
William Wallace D'Andurand Bellin was born in Providence, RI, May 25, 1919. He was a graduate of the Rhode Island School of Design, Department of Architecture (1937-41), where he gained experience designing settings and costumes for theater pageants and plays, especially influenced by Grace L. Ripley. During the same years, he did packaging design and architectural renderings in Providence, RI. Bellin also completed one year of study in motion picture set and costume design at the Chouinard Art Institute in Los Angeles. From 1942-45, he worked as an engineering production illustrator at the Douglas Aircraft Company's El Segundo location. During this time, he was active as an actor and artist with local semi-professional companies. After a brief stay in New York (1946), Bellin returned to Los Angeles, and in 1947, he began his association with Margaret Buxton's Originals, a design firm specializing in display treatments for commercial and private properties. While at Buxton's he worked as a head designer and sample technician on a variety of projects, including displays and murals for Robinsons and The Broadway department stores.
In 1950, Bellin joined the library at the University of California, Los Angeles (UCLA) as a staff artist and curator of maps, while simultaneously continuing his work for Margaret Buxton until her retirement in 1954. At UCLA, Bellin was primarily responsible for designing publications, posters, and exhibits related to library activities. He also designed the library seal and endpapers that are still found in books throughout the library's collection. Bellin enrolled in the UCLA Theater Arts Department, and though he was initially occupied with acting, he was soon both acting and designing costumes and sets for several UCLA productions, including Caesar and Cleopatra (1956) and Henry IV, Part One. After graduating Phi Beta Kappa in 1957, he was employed by the Los Angeles and San Francisco Civic Light Operas as a production assistant to designer George Jenkins on Annie Get Your Gun and Ariadne auf Naxos.
Bellin moved to New York in 1958, and over the next several decades, he worked on many theater productions in various capacities, including scenic, costume, and prop design. He continued his association with George Jenkins on projects such as Cue for Passion (1958), Tall Story (1959), and A Thousand Clowns (1962). He also built up a small scenic, costumes, and props business making statues, armor, masks, and jewelry for productions including Caligula (1960), The Tempest (1960), and The Royal Hunt of the Sun.
In 1975, Bellin became a scenic consultant for various enterprises produced by Irvin and Kenneth Feld, including Ringling Bros. and Barnum Bailey Circus, Ice Follies and Holidays on Ice Combined Shows, and Siegfried and Roy: Beyond Belief. He designed scenic elements, floats, and props. In the 1990s, Bellin served as a design consultant for the Sarasota Ballet, creating costumes for Peter and the Wolf (ca. 1992-93) and Walpurgis Night (1993-94). William Bellin died of congestive heart failure on July 18, 1995 in Sarasota, FL.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of materials reflecting the career of graphic artist and designer William Bellin. The bulk of the collection relates to his professional career as a costume, prop and set designer in the performing arts industry. Included are blueline set drawings, sketches, costume designs, and playbills, first for student productions with the UCLA Theater Arts Department and, after 1958, for New York stage productions working with art director George Jenkins and others. The projects from the UCLA Theatre Arts Dept. include Caesar and Cleopatra (1956) and Henry IV, Part One (1957), among others. Various George Jenkins projects include Cue for Passion (1958), Tall Story (1959), and A Thousand Clowns (1962), to name a few.
There is a small amount of papers along with unidentified snapshots, mainly of floats, props, and scenic elements designed by Bellin for several Irvin and Kenneth Feld productions (aka Feld Productions), including Ringling Bros. and Barnum Bailey Circus, Ice Follies, and Siegfried and Roy. Additionally, there is a small amount of professional display material, which includes photographs and color transparencies of displays and murals for Margaret Buxton's Originals, mostly created for The Broadway department store. There are also a small number of graphic design samples for UCLA library-related projects. Of special interest is the manuscript for an unpublished technical manual written by Bellin, which focuses on the design of props, costumes, and scenic elements for theater and motion pictures. Personal/biographical material comprises Bellin's education and correspondence with friends or former associates. All folder/file titles for the collection were supplied by the processor.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Series 1. Acting
Series 2. Correspondence
Series 3. Education
Series 4. Display Designs for Margaret Buxton's Originals
Series 5. Graphic Design and Illustration
Series 6. Performance Design
Series 7. Professional Affiliations
Series 8. Resumes
Series 9. Writings by Bellin
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Bellin, William--Archives; Costume designers--United States--Archival resources.; Set designers--United States--Archival resources.
Genres and Forms of Material
Costume design drawings; design drawings
Container List
- Series 1. Acting, 1953-1956; (Boxes1-4)
  The series includes eight playbills for UCLA Theater Arts productions in which Bellin is credited as an actor. He appeared in the productions while attending UCLA during the 1950s. Productions include: The Broken Stairway, Dona Elena, The Front Page, Montezuma, Treasure Island, Van Druten and The Light Touch. The series is arranged alphabetically by production titles.
  - UCLA
    - UCLA Theater Arts productions - playbills/programs with acting credits for W.B. (1 of 2) (5 items), 1953-56; The Broken Stairway, The Front Page, Montezuma, Treasure Island, Van Druten and the Light Touch. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - UCLA Theater Arts productions - playbills/programs with acting credits for W.B. (2 of 2) (3 items), 1955; Dona Elena. (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Series 2. Correspondence, ca. 1960-ca. 1990s; (Boxes 1-3, 23)
  The series is organized into three subseries: Subseries 1. Incoming Letters; Subseries 2. Outgoing Letters; and Subseries 3. Norah Jones' Correspondence. Subseries 1, Incoming Letters include two letters from friends and former associates, Vikki Kite and James V. Mink and are arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Subseries 2, Outgoing Letters include a draft letter to Vikki Kite as well as a draft letter to Edward Hearn, documenting Bellin's work as a design assistant on Broadway productions through the 1960s. Files are organized alphabetically by recipient. Subseries 3, Norah Jones Correspondence, was added to the collection in 2006 by Norah Jones, who was a close friend to Bellin. The subseries is arranged alphabetically by correspondent and includes letters, postcards, brief notes, and clippings sent to Jones from Bellin, along with a small amount of items from Lawrence Clark Powell and Vikki Kite, in regards to Bellin's death. The correspondence from Bellin to Jones reflects his thoughts and opinions on assorted topics and projects (in which he was involved). In some instances, letters appear to be missing pages.
  - Incoming Letters
    - Kite, Vikki - letters and cards to W.B., 1980s-90s; Primarily holiday cards. (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Mink, Jim - letter to W.B. with enclosure, 1986 Sep-Oct; Enclosure is an article about W.B. in the UCLA Librarian, Volume 39, Number 5. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Outgoing Letters
    - Hearn, Edward - draft letter from W.B., no date (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Kite, Vikki - draft letter from W.B., no date (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Norah Jones Correspondence
    - Bellin, William - 1960s correspondence to Norah Jones regarding several projects, 1960-62; Mostly regarding the making of armor, Thirteen Daughters, A Thousand Clowns, and Song of Norway, among others. (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Bellin, William - 1960s correspondence to Norah Jones several topics, 1963-69; Mostly regarding Erte, Mame, and Royal Hunt of the Sun, among others. (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - Bellin, William - correspondence to Norah Jones regarding A Masked Ball opera, 1962; With press clippings and program. Opera also known as "Un Ballo in Maschera." (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Bellin, William - correspondence to Norah Jones regarding Aida, 1962; With small swatch of fabric. (Box 23, Folder 14)
    - Bellin, William - correspondence to Norah Jones regarding Camelot, 1960; With clipping. (Box 23, Folder 11)
    - Bellin, William - correspondence to Norah Jones regarding early painting by Bellin, no date; Photocopy of note and clipping (clipping dated 25 May 1941). (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Bellin, William - correspondence to Norah Jones regarding Feld/(Ringling Bros.) work (mostly), 1980s; Mostly regarding the circus (with small fabric swatches), Mario Cooper, and Siegfried and Roy, among others. (Box 23, Folder 9)
    - Bellin, William - correspondence to Norah Jones regarding Feld/Ringling Bros. work (mostly), 1970s (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - Bellin, William - correspondence to Norah Jones regarding High Spirits., 1963; With playbill. (Box 23, Folder 15)
    - Bellin, William - correspondence to Norah Jones regarding Paradise Island, 1961 Jun-July (Box 23, Folder 13)
    - Bellin, William - correspondence to Norah Jones regarding Sarasota Ballet, 1990s; With opinions about American politics. (Box 23, Folder 10)
    - Bellin, William - correspondence to Norah Jones regarding Thirteen Daughters, 1961; With clipping. (Box 23, Folder 12)
    - Bellin, William - correspondence to Norah Jones regarding United Scenic Artists Entrance Examination, 1971; With copy of exam from 1971. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Bellin, William - letter to Norah Jones regarding Anchor and Bull masthead, 1985 (Box 23, Folder 17)
    - Bellin, William - letter to Norah Jones regarding Frances Clarke Sayers bookplate, 1990 (Box 23, Folder 19)
    - Bellin, William - letter to Norah Jones regarding L.C.P. bookplate, 1985; With bookplate design ideas. (Box 23, Folder 18)
    - Bellin, William - letters to Norah Jones regarding Sarasota Ballet's Peter and the Wolf, ca. 1991; With clipping. (Box 23, Folder 20)
    - Bellin, William - letters to Norah Jones regarding Sarasota Ballet's The Nutcracker, 1991-92; With clippings. (Box 23, Folder 21)
    - Bellin, William - undated correspondence to Norah Jones, no date (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Kite, Vikki - letter to Norah Jones regarding Bellin's death, 1995 Sep; With a hand printed copy of the original letter from Norah Jones to Vikki Kite, regarding the death of W.B. (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Powell, Lawrence Clark - card to Norah Jones regarding Bellin's death, 1995 Oct; With bookplate designed for L.C.P. by W.B. (Includes a transcription of the handwritten card from L.C.P.). (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Powell, Lawrence Clark - correspondence to Norah Jones regarding Anchor and Bull masthead, 1985; Note with Anchor and Bull newsletter featuring article on W.B. (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Powell, Lawrence Clark - letter to Norah Jones and book titled Ex Libris: Notes on My Family's Bookplates written by LCP, 1986 Nov 11; With bookplate designed for L.C.P. by W.B. (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Series 3. Education, 1930-1957; (Box 1)
  The series included includes a program for an elementary school revue in which Bellin performed, an obituary of Grace L. Ripley, an instructor at the Rhode Island School of Design, and Bellin's diploma and certificate of honors from UCLA. The files are arranged alphabetically.
    - "Kiddie Revue" - program for school event with W.B., 1930 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bachelor of Arts diploma and certificate of honors from UCLA, 1956-57; With award from Theatre Arts Department. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Grace Ripley - obituary (instructor from the Rhode Island School of Design), no date (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series 4. Display Designs for Margaret Buxton's Originals, ca. 1940s; (Boxes 1, 4, 6)
  The series is comprised of materials related to Bellin's design work for Margaret Buxton's Originals, a Los Angeles display firm. Bellin was associated with Buxton's from 1947-54 and worked on a variety of projects. Included are photographs and color transparencies of display treatments and murals created for The Broadway department store, as well as photographs of display objects for unknown projects. Unless otherwise noted, it is believed that Bellin was responsible for designing all of the items in this series. Files are arranged alphabetically.
    - Art of Display (The) - fliers, 1947; Printed ephemera promoting open house at Buxton's studio and postcard of Coty Paris Salon, Los Angeles. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Broadway department store - matted photographs of display pieces and murals (5 items), 1947-49; With matted Art of Display flier which is labeled as an advertisement designed for Buxton's. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Broadway department store - photographs of display murals (4 items), no date (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Broadway department store - transparencies of display murals (3 items), 1948 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Unidentified project - color transparencies of female model among hanging display pieces (3 items), no date (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Unidentified project - photographs of display pieces (15 items), no date (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Unidentified project - transparency-type items (4 items), no date; Appear to be fireworks sparks. White on clear plastic-type material. (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Series 5. Graphic Design and Illustration, 1944-1990; (Boxes 1-3)
  The bulk of the series consists of drawings and printed ephemera related to designs created by Bellin. The series is arranged chronologically into four subseries: Subseries 1. Douglas Aircraft Company (1940s); Subseries 2. UCLA (mostly 1950s); Subseries 3. Lawrence Clark Powell (mostly 1980s); and Subseries 4. Unknown Project (no date). Douglas Aircraft Company material includes employment records created during Bellin's tenure as an engineering production illustrator from 1942-45. UCLA files consist mostly of designs for the library, believed to be produced by Bellin in his work as a library staff artist during the 1950s. Of interest are the library seal and endpapers that are still found in the library's book collection. Lawrence Clark Powell material contains samples of work commissioned to Bellin during the 1980s, including designs for a personal bookplate and the masthead of The Anchor and Bull, a newsletter of the Friends of the University of Arizona Library. The unknown projects is an untitled sketch of flowers by Bellin. The files within each subseries are arranged alphabetically by project title.
  - Douglas Aircraft Company, Inc.
    - Employment records, 1944-45; With "Employe" analysis reports, personnel forms, and printed ephemera. Also includes recommendation for W.B. to U.S. Navy. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - UCLA
    - Clark Library - newsletter graphic and other printed ephemera with graphic design by W.B., 1950s and 1994 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Edward Niles Hooker Memorial Collection in the UCLA Performing Arts Special Collections - bookplate design, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Know Your Library - library user guides with cover and drawings by W.B. (2 items), 1951, 1957-58 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Library Seal and endpaper designs, no date (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Reserve book room (Room 145, former main library) - photograph of signs designed by W.B., ca. 1953; With letter of thanks from Andrew Horn. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Small placards created by W.B. for the UCLA Library, 1951-57 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - UCLA Library-related printed ephemera, 1951-55, 1981; Many items with graphic designs by W.B. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Lawrence Clark Powell
    - Bookplate design for Lawrence Clark Powell, ca. 1985 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Southwest: Three Definitions - book by Lawrence Clark Powell., 1990 Mar 12; First page inscribed to W.B. by L.C.P. Title page includes illustration of "Heart of the Southwest" map created by W.B. (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - University of Arizona - Anchor and Bull masthead design commissioned by Lawrence Clark Powell., 1984-85 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - University of Arizona - Books of the Southwest publication, ca. 1987; Submitted to W.B. by L.C.P. for comments on design. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Unknown Project
    - Sketch of flowers by W.B., 1990 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Series 6. Performance Design, 1954-1996; (Boxes 1-22)
  Scope and Content
  This series consists of production materials related to a number of theater and television projects with which it is believed Bellin was involved during the 1940s to 1990s. The material has been arranged into five subseries: Subseries 1. Feld Productions (ca. late 1970s-early 1980s); Subseries 2. George Jenkins Projects (ca. late 1950s-1962); Subseries 3. Sarasota Ballet (early 1990s); Subseries 4. Other Stage and Television Productions (ca. 1950s-1960s); and Subseries 5. UCLA (ca.1950s). Files within each subseries are arranged alphabetically by project title. For instances where a project title could not be determined, the processor supplied the title of Unidentified project. The Feld Productions files are comprised of blueline drawings, photographs, and printed ephemera for Irvin and Kenneth Feld productions from 1979-early 1980s and includes material for Ringling Bros. and Barnum Bailey Circus, the Ice Follies and Holidays on Ice Combined Shows, and Siegfried and Roy: Beyond Belief. The bulk of George Jenkins Projects material consists of blueline copy drawings for stage and television productions, as well as a small amount of playbills, and/or copies of sketches (for selected titles). In the majority of the playbills, Bellin is credited as an assistant to Jenkins. Includes material for Two for the Seesaw (1957-58), The Miracle Worker (1959), Music with Mary Martin (1959), and A Thousand Clowns (1962), among others. Of particular note in the Sarasota Ballet files are Bellin's costume sketches for Peter and the Wolf (ca. 1992-93) and Walpurgis Night (1993-94) (production titles identified by a Sarasota Ballet archivist January, 2006). The UCLA projects include set plans, original costume sketches, and playbills for UCLA Theater Arts Department productions of Caesar and Cleopatra, The Love of Four Colonels, and Henry IV, Part One (1954-57). The Other Stage and Television Projects includes a mixture of material created for stage and television productions, not identified with a particular producer or production company. Included are blueline copy drawings, occasional playbills, stencils, and/or prop sketches for stage productions such as Caligula (1960), Fade Out Fade In (1964), and T raveller Without Luggage (1964). Additionally, there are blueline drawings for one episode of the television project CBS' Studio One. There are also a small number of items that are not identified.
  - Feld Productions
    - Ice Follies and Holiday on Ice - press clippings and thank you letter from Kenneth Feld, 1980; . (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Ice Follies and Holiday on Ice Combined Shows - snapshots from unidentified ice show (11), no date (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Ringling Bros. and Barnum Bailey Circus - unidentified project/performance - blueline drawing, no date; Train cab and boiler. (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Ringling Bros. and Barnum Bailey Circus unidentified performers - slides (8 items), no date (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Ringling Bros. and Barnum Bailey Circus unidentified project/performance - notes, idea sketches, and negatives of prop sketches, 1980-81; With letter from Kenneth Feld to W.B. regarding employment (original and photocopy). (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Ringling Bros. and Barnum Bailey Circus unidentified project/performance - snapshots (133), no date; Mostly scenic elements, floats, and props. (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Ringling Bros. and Barnum Bailey Circus unidentified project/performance - snapshots (162), no date; Mostly scenic elements, floats, and props. (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Ringling Bros. and Barnum Bailey Circus unidentified project/performance - snapshots (5), no date (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Ringling Bros. and Barnum Bailey Circus unidentified project/performance - snapshots (80), ca. 1979; Mostly scenic elements, floats, and props. Appear to be reprints. (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Siegfried and Roy: Beyond Belief - blueline drawings of set and scenic elements (3 items), no date (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Siegfried and Roy: Beyond Belief - program and photocopied press clippings, ca. 1981 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - George Jenkins Projects
    - 13 Daughters - blueline drawings (6 items), 1960-61; Master plan, boats on beach, hut, valley scene, Chun's house, Malia's room, and palace. (Box 18, Folder 0)
    - 13 Daughters - original artwork of scenery details, no date; Designs for Chief's pavilion and Chun's house. (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Annie Get Your Gun - playbills (2 items), 1957 Sep-Oct; One each for San Francisco and Los Angeles Civic Light Opera. (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Annie Get Your Gun (television project) - blueline drawings (4 items), 1957; Rough ground plans. (Box 21, Folder 0)
    - Around the World in 80 Days - playbill, no date (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Catstick - blueline drawings (6 items), 1960; Primarily of front door, bay window, ground plan and elevations. (Box 8, Folder 0)
    - Catstick - playbill, 1961 Jan 9 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Critic's Choice - blueline drawings (6 items), 1960; Primarily of stairs, elevations, and electrical layout. (Box 8, Folder 0)
    - Cue for Passion - blueline drawings (6 items), 1958; Masking, portal, and Nicholson's living room. (Box 8, Folder 0)
    - Cue for Passion - playbills (2 items), 1958 Nov (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Desk Set (The) - blueline drawings (2 items), 1955; General plan and Miss Watson's Office. (Box 8, Folder 0)
    - Happiest Millionaire (The) - blueline drawings (8 items), 1956; Primarily of solarium, ceiling, and elevations. (Box 9, Folder 0)
    - Hit the Deck - blueline drawings (28 items), 1960 Jan-Apr; Primarily of yacht club, Lulu's coffee shop, U.S.S. Nevada, and Roberto's bar. (Box 10, Folder 0)